As soon as I niched down as a freelance
writer, I went from charging $20 to
write blog posts to [music] charging
$2,000 to write thought leadership
articles for founders and executives.
And today, I run the largest training
program on the internet for writers who
want to niche down, specialize in a
service, and charge a premium. It's
called Premium Ghost Writing Academy.
And in this video, I'm going to walk you
through the same road map that I walk
every writer in our program through for
free. So, by the end, you know how to
niche down in the world of content
writing, too. Okay, let's start with why
niching down makes you so much money.
And whenever I talk about this, I like
explaining it with a really simple
story. So, let's say uh you just bought
a new house, okay? And in this house,
you have a beautiful stained glass
window and one day your neighbor's kid
fires a hockey puck through it, shatters
everywhere. Now, which person are you
going to hire to fix that stained glass
window? Are you going to hire the
generalist? So, the person who says, "I
can fix any window." Or are you going to
hire the specialist who says, "Actually,
I don't do all those other windows. I
only specialize in fixing stained glass
windows." Which person are you going to
hire? You are going to hire the second
person every single time because you
have a very specific problem and you're
looking for someone who solves that
specific problem, right? And this is why
niching down makes you so much money is
a it instantly differentiates you. B,
when that person who has that specific
problem is looking for a solution,
they're going to assume that you're the
best possible person for the job. And C,
there's actually three reasons why
niching down makes you so much money.
So, I want to walk you through each one.
So, the first is pricing power. Okay?
When you are a specialist, you
inherently can charge more than
generalists. This is why as soon as I
stopped calling myself a freelance
writer and I started calling myself a
ghostwriter for founders specializing in
writing thought leadership articles, I
went from charging $20 per blog post to
charging upwards of $2,000 per article.
Now, nothing was different about the
work. And this this didn't happen 10
years later. In both cases, I was still
26 years old and I was writing 800
words.
Same work, same age, same experience.
The only difference is that I called
myself a freelance writer who did
everything here and here. I said I am a
ghost writer who specializes in
ghostwriting thought leadership articles
for founders. That's the only
difference. This is why being a
specialist is so important because it
gives you pricing power. instantly
differentiates you from everyone else.
Real quick, if you want to write online
but aren't sure where to start, click
the link in the description of this
video and check out
startwritingline.com.
This is a free master class I put
together sharing all of our most helpful
frameworks for beginners, like proven
hooks to capture your target readers
attention, where to write online to get
the most distribution on your work, and
little growth hacking tips to build your
social audience and email list faster.
Over a 100,000 writers have gone through
this free master class and many even
send us emails afterwards thanking us
for sharing such valuable information
for free. So click the link below this
video to check it out and make this year
the year you start seeing success from
your writing online.
The second way that specializing makes
you more money is this is how you create
efficiencies. Okay, if you are providing
the same service over and over and over
again. So here I was writing thought
leadership articles. Okay, this was the
only thing that we did. We didn't do
newsletters. We didn't do short form
content. We didn't do video scripts. We
didn't do landing pages. The only thing
we did was 800word thought leadership
articles, okay? We scaled my agency to
essentially the size of a small
publication. In any given month, we were
producing more articles in Inc.
Magazine, Forbes. Okay? So, we became
very successful at doing this. And the
reason that my agency was able to grow
to over two million in annual revenue,
right, we had 20 plus employees. We had
80 plus clients. The reason we were able
to do that is because we were doing the
same thing over and over and over and
over and over again. Okay. So, every
team, just to show you how this worked,
every team was we had a writer and we
had an editor. And we knew that each
team could maybe handle, let's see,
probably about 10 clients. And so, as we
scaled, what did we do? We just took
this team and we just hit copy paste and
we just duplicated it. We did the same
thing over and over again. That is how
you create efficiency. It is very
difficult for you to create efficiencies
when you say that you do everything
because every client is different. Every
client is in a different industry.
You're providing a different service.
You have no ability to create
efficiency. And so efficiency is what
limits two things. It limits your time
and it limits the amount of money that
you can make. On the time front, the
more you can templatize, the more that
you can get done in the same amount of
time, right? So, if you have five
clients and you're doing the same thing
over and over and over again, well, now
you have a bunch of free time because
you can create templates, you can create
processes, you now you can create
automations, you can use AI to help you,
right? If you're not doing the same
thing over and over again, you're doing
everything manually and you have a very
high switching cost. Which leads to the
third, which is increasing profit.
So, as you have pricing power, which
allows you to dominate a niche, and as
you build efficiencies, this is what
allows you to take on more clients,
which means you can make more money. So,
maybe a freelance writer goes, "Oh, I
can only handle three clients at a
time." But you go, you know, I'm I've
created efficiencies. I'm doing the same
thing over and over again. I actually
can handle 10 clients. That's a huge
profit difference, right? This person is
severely limited. Now you are able to
make three times more than the average
freelance writer. And so niching down
it's not just a positioning choice.
Niching down is actually how you unlock
these different tanches of monetization.
Okay this is really really important.
Now whenever I explain this a question
that people ask often is okay Cole that
all makes sense but how am I supposed to
niche down? Well, especially if you're
providing a writing service, you want to
think about niching down in two
different ways.
You could niche down by industry or you
could niche down by service. Now, the
goal is you actually want to do both.
Okay? So, I'll give you an example. When
I was building my agency, we got to a
point where I realized that our sweet
spot, our true niche was I Ghostright or
my agency, we ghostright 800word thought
leadership articles specifically for
series A to series B startup founders.
Hey, by the way, if you're brand new to
the world of ghostwriting, maybe you've
heard the term but aren't really sure
what it is or how it's different from
copywriting or content writing, check
out premium ghostwritingbloopprint.com.
It's in the description below. Okay,
this is a free master class that I've
put together for writers who want to
monetize their skills and love for
writing with ghostriting. This is what I
did. And ghostriting completely changed
my life. It's how I quit my job. It's
how I quadrupled the amount of money I
was making. It's how I've gotten to work
with so many smart, amazing people, but
also have time for my own writing, like
writing this book, The Art and Business
of Ghostwriting. Anyways, check it out.
If you're at all interested in making
money from your writing, I would really
encourage you to get into ghostriting.
And this free premium ghost trading
blueprint in the description below is
the best place to start. Yes, we also
worked with executives. We worked with
New York Times bestselling authors. We
we even worked with Olympic athletes and
Grammy winning musicians. Okay, we we
did all sorts of stuff, but our sweet
spot industry was actually working with
startup founders that had just raised a
really big series A. Okay, so yes, you
can get this specific. If you're stuck
though, I think it is much easier to
start with the service. Okay. And
there's really three services I
recommend everyone starts with today. So
one is
educational email course ghostwriting.
So this is a free optin. So we actually
use these for all of our different
verticals in our different businesses.
So if you go to startwritingonline.com
for example, we have a 5-day educational
email course for free that teaches
people our frameworks on how to start
writing online. We also have an EEC. So
this would be start writing online. We
also have one for ghostwriting. If you
go to ghostwritingbloopprint.com,
you will see our free educational email
course on how you can get started
ghostwriting. These are incredibly
effective optins. All right, so most
people don't realize that the fastest
way to build a newsletter or the fastest
way to build your newsletter list is
actually not sending people directly to
a newsletter. It's sending them to a
highvalue free opt-in and then at the
end of the EEC you put everyone inside
of your newsletter. Okay, so you can get
paid a lot of money to build these. In
in our premium ghost writing academy,
for example, we teach ghostriters how to
build these educational email courses
and sell them to businesses. We show
them how to charge five grand, seven
grand, 10 grand per EC, so per project.
The second service is newsletters.
So newsletter ghostwriting is really,
really effective and very, very
important. So what happens when you get
someone's email? Well, they go through a
5-day educational email course. You
don't want them to never hear from you
ever again. So you should put them into
a high-value newsletter. That newsletter
is how you nurture them, right? You
could you could remind them, hey, I have
this digital product for sale. Hey, I
wrote these books. You know, how do you
think I've driven so many sales for
these books? The art and business of
ghost writing and the art and business
of online writing. Well, inside our EEC,
we mention them. And then after the EEC,
we n we nurture people forever in our
newsletter and also mention them, right?
So, this creates a really great
long-term funnel for any product, any
service. This is how you get people on
sales calls, right? Newsletters are
foundational for every business. And
then third, if you have an EC and you're
nurturing people on the newsletter,
what's the last thing you need? Well,
you need traffic, right? Everyone now
wants to build a personal brand.
Everyone wants to drive organic traffic.
We're going to drive traffic from social
to the educational email course. get
more people on our newsletter, nurture
them via newsletter, and the cycle
repeats. If you are a writer today and
you are not providing one or two of
these services, you are leaving a
tremendous amount of money on the table
because every single business needs all
three of these. And the takeaway
shouldn't be, oh, I have to do all three
of them. No, you could build a
sevenfigure agency just building
educational email courses. You could
build a sevenfigure agency just
ghostwriting newsletters. You can build
a seven-figure agency just writing short
form content on social platforms. and
not just every social platform, just
LinkedIn or just X, right? So
specializing is really important. I
would say that it is much easier to
start by picking a service that you want
to specialize in first because then over
time you can discover which industry do
you want to play in. So here's why the
industry component is so important. Most
people don't realize that every industry
has its own vernacular. Every industry
has its own slang. Every industry has
its own rules. Every industry has its
own regulations. Okay? So, for example,
if you were to ghostrite in the finance
industry. Well, the average person might
not realize that when you're writing for
people in finance, if you're writing for
uh like a fintech startup, there are
actually laws about what you can and
can't say. So, when you're writing
content, very often these companies will
run everything you write, blog post,
newsletters, short form content, doesn't
matter. They will run it through their
legal team. If you are a writer who
specializes in this industry and you
know the lingo of the finance industry
and you know the laws and regulations,
you are 10 times more valuable than the
average freelancer who goes, "I'll write
whatever you want, but I don't really
have experience in that industry." You
have what I like to call an information
advantage.
An information advantage is not I'm an
expert with 20 years of experience. An
information advantage is just, hey, you
know, I've spent some time in this
industry. I know how people talk. I know
the lingo and I also understand sort of
the laws and regulations. Health and
wellness
is another big one. There are laws about
what you can and can't say about the
probiotic that you're helping some
company sell, right? You can't say, "Oh,
this probiotic
cures cancer." You can't say that,
right? And so, if you don't know those
things, then how are you supposed to
write in that industry? And this is why
information advantage is so important.
And so yeah, start by specializing in a
service, but over time you also want to
specialize in an industry.
Now, of course, every time I explain
this, the big objection I hear is,
"Yeah, but Cole, if I get that specific,
if I get that specific about a service,
if I get that specific about an
industry, that's going to limit my
opportunity. I'm not going to have
enough people to work with." And I hope
you've realized by this point in the
video that that is not true. But let me
just prove it one more one more way. So
when you niche down, you create what's
called a niche constellation, a client
constellation. Okay? What this means is
let's say that you specialize in
newsletters. Okay?
And let's say over time you learn that
your industry is real estate. Okay?
Now, that might seem really specific
until you start building the
constellation in real estate. Think
about all the different sub audiences
that you could tap into. You could tap
into real estate agents. You could tap
into real estate marketing agencies. You
could tap into real estate brokers for
commercial properties. You could
specialize in working with real estate
brokers in multif family, right?
Apartment complexes. And with
newsletters, why can't you provide not
just newsletters, but you could also
provide EC's and you could also provide
other sequences, right? Maybe the person
doesn't just need a newsletter. They
need an upsell sequence. They need a
downell sequence. They need a book a
call sequence. Your opportunity is not
limited. All you need to do is have a
tip of the spear, something that you
specialize in. And then you start to
realize, actually, there's all these sub
audiences that I can tap into. Okay? And
as you start to build this niche
constellation, you realize that niching
down is the path to tapping into all
these sub audiences. But if you just say
real quick, if you want to start writing
online but haven't yet, or maybe you've
been writing online but just aren't
seeing much traction, I would love to
help. Okay? I've been writing online for
over a decade. I've generated over a
billion views on my writing. And in the
description below, if you go to
startwritingonline.com,
I've put together a free master class
sharing my favorite and most effective
digital writing frameworks. This is
everything you need to be successful in
the digital age as a writer. So, just
click the link below and check it out. I
do everything. Nobody can hear you. No
one knows what to do with you. No one
knows where to put you in their brain.
So, this is why one of the big things
that I stress in our premium ghost
writing academy is you should start by
picking a specific service. Pick
something that you want to spend two
years of your life getting really good
at and then look to apply it to a
specific industry. And as you do that,
realize your opportunity is not limited.
You have all these other sub audiences
that you can tap into.
Okay, to end this, I want to explain why
this is so hard for people.
You might think that this is a funnel,
but it's not. It's a red solo cup. Okay.
So, pretend that you have a factory and
the only thing you do is make red
plastic solo cups. Okay. And one day a
little old woman comes in and she goes,
"I am looking for a tiny little
like marble teacup. I want you to create
a specialized China marble teacup. Like
I want it just like my grandma before me
had. I want you to make it just for me.
You would go, that's not what we do
here. We make we make a million
red plastic solo cups a month. How on
earth am I supposed to change all of my
manufacturing and all of my processes to
make this one specific type of cup that
you're looking for? You wouldn't adjust
everything that you're doing for this
person. You would say, "I'm sorry,
that's not what we do here. I wish you
all the best. There's someone down the
street who can help you." And yet, this
is what writers do every single day. A
writer goes, "I specialize in
newsletters, right? This is your red
plastic solo cup." And then someone
comes in and goes, "Actually, I'm
looking for Instagram scripts."
And what the writer does is they go,
"Oh, you know what? That's great news.
I've decided I completely give up on
newsletters. I'm going to do this, too."
And they instantly shut down their
factory. And so, the skill to build is
learning how to say no, right? You can't
end up building uh dominance in a niche.
You can't end up building a roster of
clients where you do the same thing over
and over and over again if you're
constantly crushing your efficiencies
and crushing your pricing power and
crushing your profit by saying yes to
every single person who walks into your
factory. You can't do it. And so
fundamentally, you have to learn the
skill of saying no because every time
you say no, you're not limiting your
opportunity. What you're doing is you're
protecting your capacity. You want to
protect the capacity that you have and
go no, no, no. instead of taking on this
other client, I'm gonna spend three more
hours, five more hours, 10 more hours
going and getting the right person so
that I can keep doing the same thing
over and over and over again inside my
factory. This is a very hard skill for
people to build. And even after someone
lands a client, two clients, five
clients, 10 clients, even after they hit
10 grand a month, I have coached so many
writers through this problem and it
never goes away. This problem exists at
the very beginning. It exists when you
hit 10 grand a month. It exists when you
hit 20 grand a month. It exists at 100
grand a month because every time you
take a step forward and as you get
better and better at things, you attract
new opportunities. And so you're going
to get confronted with, hey, but could
you also do this random thing for me?
You're going to get confronted with that
over and over and over again, which is
why you have to have clarity on what you
specialize in, and you have to build the
skill of saying no.
>> [music]